so this is a question from a friend who
is suffering from
Fear he says I constantly think about
all the ways I could suffer in the
future and try to put things in place to
prevent those future
sufferings but no matter what I do I
can't eliminate uncertainty or control
every possible danger how do I stop my
mind from endlessly trying
how can I learn to accept the
unknown well the
result all of that which is described is
really a
result of the mind that's still not
under your
control but you can't you can't teach
your mind you can't tame your mind
simply by wishing it stops and trying to
get rid of the things the B is it you
need to start training it
so then you have to start looking into
why is my mind still not pliable as the
suit would say why is it still not
listening to
me why why does it still revolve around
the same um fearful scenarios and uh like
same um fearful scenarios and uh like
what is it that I'm doing that's that's
um that's enabling
it because usually
people would like to have the view well
not they have a view but they would like
to be able to go through um day-to-day
life simply uh not having to think about
simply uh not having to think about
these things unless they come up
unpleasant things like fear anxiety and
so on and when they do come up then they
want to be able to not think about them
per will like oh I just wish this goes
away if M would only stop thinking about
it but mind thinking about those fearful
aspects and so on it's that's not the
problem that's just the symptom of an
under problem so it's just showing you that
problem so it's just showing you that
the problem is elsewhere and you're not
addressing
it and in particular with this person he
says how can I
equanimous or let go of the body while
taking reasonable measures to protect it
well you can equanimous let go of the
body by not holding on to it through
your desires through your intentional Acts
desires through your intentional Acts
so if you're still if your if your
behavior and speech is not
purified if if that intentionality
behind your actions is not um
discerned you can wish all you want and
and and theorize how to you know take
control how to be equanimous what to do
in this situation fundamentally you're
just managing the
symptoms so if the fear still overwhelms
you it's because the mind is still still
wilder than you are able to tame
it so when such experiences come well
the most you can do during those those
those intense periods is don't make
things worse through acts of body or
speech mentally as I said try to um try
to endure these things on that level
without like being filled
with pressure and panic like I must get
rid of this as soon as possible cuz
that's going to make it worse but then
when those episodes uh
subside then you got to start
reevaluating your whole life
everything like what anxiety or fear
shows you it's not a one little problem
uh just uh on on that mundane level it
just reveals you the whole nature of
your existence the fact that you're
liable to fear the fact that you're
liable to the mind turning against you
uh even if you did everything right
seemingly in the worldly manner so you
really want to start reevaluating your
actions uh your Ambitions your
aspirations and and yeah then put
everything down and see which one is is
uh carries more worth to you um because
if you are willingly intentionally
engaging with with
with with
desires act out of ill
will careless in regard to speech do not
bear that responsibility of your
intentions and actions on that mental
level but instantly want to psychologize
get rid of it uh deal with it so it
doesn't bother you uh you are enabling
the Wilderness of your mind you are not
really um teaching it you're not really
conveying the message to the mind so
that it calms
down and with this like like you know
fear of the
uncertain but it was always uncertain
things things were not more uncertain
today than they were yesterday or the
day you were born it's just that under
certain circumstances you become more
aware of the same
uncertainty and that's what you perceive
oh this is the bothersome aspect of it
but it's really only because the threat
of uncertainty can affect you because
you still hold on to things are are
established upon things uh have
appropriated things that are not in your
control that are subject to that
uncertainty so then when uncertainty
reveals itself that's when you feel like
oh you know you are under a
threat and that's the whole you know the
the fundamental contemplations about
sickness aging death inevitability of
change and you want to be seeing and
Discerning whether there are things that
you hold there that you are not
questioning that you're taking for
granted that would that will be taken
away uh by change when it occurs and
then basically let go of them before
that happens
but it's quite yeah it's quite difficult
if you are well usually you're in a
comfort zone and you're shielding
yourself that reality it's like only
when sickness comes start realizing oh
man well that's what I'm saying you you
actually you want to start thinking
about these things before these episodes
occur where where you know you might
have just enough room to not act out of
the pressure when it gets too much
you're certainly not going to have
enough mental space to be able to
maintain perspective and see through the
origin and all these other things we
talk about cuz you just haven't been
training it yeah so don't wait until you
get sick or yeah don't wait until you
get sick but start bringing up these
contexts in a controlled manner on the
basis of your
virtue um and sense restraint and Taming
of the senses and start recognizing
value in that it's not going to be
purified or perfected overnight but
that's not an excuse to dilute it as
something to Aspire for or or to even
like completely dismiss
it it's like those keeping the precepts
saying no to yourself Cent straint it's
like that gentle exposure to reality to
what's inevitable no no exactly yes
that's what it does hits you in the face
before it gets too much much yeah before
it gets too much that's the whole point
of of that whole training like you know
you can do all the meditation calming
you want if you're not addressing the
origin the inadvertently fueled origins of the
the inadvertently fueled origins of the
problem fueled through your actions all
you're doing as I said so many times
before it's like putting a plaster on a
festering wound cover yeah might look
nice and clean and uh smell uh
sterilized from the outside but on the
inside it's it's still much the same
infection getting worse